Gandhiji was a tremendous man when I used to learn a lot from him
圣雄甘地是一个伟大的人 我曾经从他那学到很多
He was not at all a hypocrite. That’s one thing
他不是个伪君子
and he was not like modern politician who says something, do something. No
他不像的现代政治家那样说些什么或做些什么
he was very outspoken and always put himself on the testing point
他非常直言不讳并总把自己放在测试中
and he used to confess if he made mistakes immediately
如果他犯错他惯于立刻承认
One very great incident I remember when I was a small child
我记得一个伟大的事件 当时我是个小孩子
They were having a meeting together
他们在一起开会
and we girls were there only sitting giving them water and things, to all the people
我们女孩子们坐在那 只是给他们端茶倒水
All the big people were there, like Jawaharlal Lal Nehru was there and also Maulana Azad All these people were sitting there
所有的大人物都在那 尼赫鲁 Maulana Azad也在 所有那些人都坐在那
They were discussing something
他们在讨论些什么
and then suddenly Mahatmaji said that, Now it’s very late. We’ll have lunch here
然后忽然甘地说 很晚了 咱们要在这吃午饭了
So they said, Yes, yes, we’ll have lunch here
所以他们说 对 对 我们在这吃午饭
They had to go to the guest house which was far away
他们要走到招待所 非常很远
So Mahatmaji asked for the Baa, his wife. She had gone out
所以甘地去叫 他的妻子 可是她已经出门了
So he got up. He had a key with him, you see, always of the store room. He opened the store room
所以他起来 他总随身带着个钥匙 储藏室钥匙他打开储藏室
and he asked the people who were in charge of cooking
他请负责做饭的人
to measure everything according to the people there are, properly and everything, you see
根据人数估算每一样东西 所有东西
and then he went. They measured it out. Everything was done and then he put the key back
他们估算出来 每件东西完成 然后他放回了钥匙
and then he went and sat there nicely
然后他回去 坐好
So these people said, “Bapu, we did not know you had to take so much trouble
那些人说 我们不知道给您找了这么多麻烦
you see, to go all the way, to measure everything out for us
你看 心甘情愿地 为我们估量每一样东西
It did not take much time, about fifteen minutes, but still
没有花太多的时间 大概十五分钟 但是仍然花了些时间
So he said, What do you think
他说 你们怎么想
This is the blood of my country. I cannot allow it to be wasted
这是我们国家的血液 我不允许浪费
See, that’s the sign of a person who understands the value of public money
看 那是一个人的标志 他明白公款的价值
That’s just ingrained in him, but those who saw him
那是在他内根深蒂固的 但那些看到他的人
also felt that look at this man who is living like a ascetic
也觉得 看看这个人生活的像一个苦行者
absolutely in the sense that he would not touch the public money
绝对的 他不会碰公款
And that is one of the keys for all the leaders. If they are absolutely above money
那是个所有领导者都有的一个钥匙 他们绝对一致的对待金钱
then only people will respect; otherwise, there is no way out
才会得到人民的尊重 否则 没有出路
But you find these days in every country so much of corruption, hypocrisy, you are really shocked
但是现在你发现在每一个国家如此多的腐败 虚伪 你真的震惊了